Thank you.
How's that?
All right.
Good to see you all.
We're continuing, for those that haven't been here, we're continuing a series on John,
the seven signs and seven wonders, you look at John, seven island statements in the book
of John.
And today we've come to a very pivotal point.
It's the center of the book of John.
Ten chapters before this cover about three years, and it covers most of his miracles
and his teachings.
And the ten chapters that come after it cover about three weeks, and they cover his glorification,
his being revealed as the Son of God of his power, as Paul called it.
The reason the apostles, the reed, Jesus, was the place he was raised from the dead, and
revealed as the Son of God of the power, and it covers over in Romans 1.
So that's what the end of John's about.
So between the three years, something kicked it into gear so that that pastor of glory would
happen.
That's the story.
So that's what we're going to talk about today.
Okay?
And we need to look at it through John's frame.
John sort of writes everything through a three-porting frame.
Okay?
John 1 says, in the beginning was the word, the word is which side of the word of God.
All things were made by him.
Without him, nothing made that was made.
In him was life, and that life was provided many.
So this creative movement for him, who all things came free, that brings life beyond life
to us.
That's the first thing that John always had in mind.
The second thing, he tells us that word between flesh and political numbers.
In the first John, first verse, he says, we knew it, we touched it, we walked around with
it, and we didn't think it was spoken, but they did, right?
He was human, that they walked around with.
So divine, human, eternal, mortal, those are two of the things that John always has in
view when he's talking.
And the third thing is the last bit of John 20, verse 31, these things I'm telling you
so that you might believe, and that believing you might have life in his name, right?
So in this divine, mortal, I'm telling you, it's going to be hard to believe, but believe
it, because in that, you will find life in his name.
And I'm telling you all this, you will believe that one thing, okay?
And this is the figure of the book where he's telling us that.
So it's in this story that he relates from his time as a community with Christ, Lazarus
raised from the dead.
I just want to put that out there up front.
That's the story.
Lazarus raised from the dead, which means an actual guy that walked around with John and
Jesus, dies, got sick and died, and Jesus brought him back some dead.
It's possible you've been in church a long time, and you kind of forget that that's an amazing
fact, but it is.
And you should re-experience that right now.
If you knew, and you're searching out Christianity, that's the kind of stuff we're claiming is
true.
John told us that was true.
That's why they believe, right?
So that's an amazing thing.
Let's just take that as writ for the moment.
And I told you that in one sentence, Lazarus brought back to life.
John writes so he can do more verses, right?
So we need to ask ourselves, looking through John's frame, the good central story of why did
you keep writing, right?
Why didn't you come to tell us, why did Jesus do this, and why did you tell us about it?
That's what we're going to look at today.
So to set it up in chapter 10, what just happened, as Jesus had been in Jerusalem for Hanukkah,
it probably says the festival of dedication in your Bible, that's Hanukkah, and so that's
for the end of December, and he had declared himself as one with God, which was true, according
to John, right?
This man who was from the beginning with God was true, but he was being blessed by things
he didn't believe, and so they were going to study him in the temple, and he had left town
to kind of lay low, he'd gone 23, 25 miles down the mountain, across the river, towards
John the Baptist's first baptist, so he's 25 miles outside Jerusalem, just waiting for
the hub of Babylon, because it's not time yet, he said, it's not yet my time.
That's when he is when Lazarus falls ill at the beginning of chapter 11, right?
So Lazarus falls ill, and his sisters, who are disciples of Christ, are so concerned and
so distraught that they're willing to risk it all and say, Jesus, you've got to come back
up to Jerusalem, where people are seeking to stone you, to help our brother.
It's that important, right?
They panicked with them, they sent a messenger out to them, and that's where the story picks
up in chapter 11.
And in verse, oh by the way, I'm going to say, we're going to walk through this chapter
today, and if the, if the verses don't keep up with me, it's my fault, we're at base,
because I'll probably move away from the outline, so it'll be a base race.
But in the fifth and sixth word in verse three, it said, he who you believe, who you love is
sick.
Your good friend is sick.
When Jesus heard this, he said, this sickness is not to end in death, but for the glory of
God, so that the Son of God may be glorified by you.
He said, this will not end in death.
The disciples heard, Lazarus won't die, because as far as they knew, things that would die end
in death, right?
So, he said, this will not end in death, and he said, why am I doing that?
So, the Son of God may be glorified.
I said, one of the things we're going to try to figure out is why Jesus did it, he tells
us in verse four, right?
But he keeps writing for four universities.
So, let's go further.
So, the question is, why is he still writing?
What else is he going to tell us?
And what does he mean by glory, right?
He said, I'm glad that you saw this, and we know that when he said, I'm glad this
happened, he means I'm glad.
That Lazarus died, so that I'll take you glorified.
That's going to be still, right?
Now, that's a kind of odd.
And how does death come out of glory?
Well, that's something that Jesus is trying to teach them, right?
Death is not the end.
This will not end in death.
But they heard, Lazarus won't die, and so they're okay with that.
Nothing significant has happened, as far as the disciples know.
So, John told us in verse five, now Jesus loved Martin and his sister Lazarus, so, which is
a conjunction, he stayed two more days, so I'm going to be a sin, right?
That sounds odd to us.
Why would you stay two days when your friend is ill, and they've asked you to come help?
The reason John put that in there is to assure us that not only John really, Jesus really
did hear about Lazarus, and he stayed for two more days, because there's something greater
afoot.
And after two days, Jesus said to his disciples, okay, now let's go to Judea again in verse
seven.
And now the disciples are worried, I don't want to go to Jerusalem.
People are looking to Stonus in Jerusalem, right?
Why do we want to go back to Bethany, which is just two miles, it's a bedroom community
around outside Jerusalem, two miles away from Jerusalem.
So, why do we want to go to Bethany where people are looking to Stonus?
And he said, well, whose answer to that is, are there not twelve hours in the day?
If anyone walks in the day, he doesn't stumble, because he sees the light of the wind.
But if anyone walks in the night, he's stumbled, because the light is not in him.
For you, chap, they said, why do we want to go to Jerusalem where people want to Stonus?
And you said, it's bright during the day.
Right?
And they said, there's no rejoinder listening to the disciples, because they're sitting there
with their mouth.
What are you talking about?
So, he goes further, he says, our friend Lazarus is falling asleep, but I go, so I'm
going to wake him out of sleep.
Doesn't help, right?
I asked you, why do we want to go to Jerusalem where people are trying to Stonus?
And you said, it's bright during the day, and Lazarus is sleeping.
I don't know why you would go there, it's not making sense to me.
Now, in verse 14, Jesus finally speaks plainly to them.
He says, Lazarus is sleeping.
And I'm glad for your sakes that I was not there when it happened, so that you might believe.
And now let's go to them.
At this moment, the disciples maybe were to say that you said he was not going to die.
They don't say that.
They say, oh great, we're going to go die with him.
Right?
That's what Thomas said.
And I'm confident that John Kitt Thomas would quote it here, because he thought it was hilarious.
Let's all go along with these made by women.
Great.
Laws of the dead, Jews of the dead, we'll all be good together.
Great plan.
They don't address that, um, Jews of the dead, this Lord Indian does.
But it's going to come to them.
Uh, when they approach Bethany, um, they find that he's already been in a tomb for four days.
That's a significant fact in verse 17.
He's already been dead for four days.
In verse 3, it's a key, it's that you're, when you make that 20 mile uphill fit on foot with a bunch of guys, that's not a day's fit.
You're going to get there on the second day.
The messenger may have got me on the first day.
It's probably cheaper than his way.
But Jesus waited two days, took a day on that fit back.
Lazarus died on the floor of the messenger over the house.
Right?
And Jesus would have known that.
And so when he said to them, this won't even dance, he already realized this is dead.
Um, Jesus said at one point in the Scriptures, unless a criminal freak falls into the ground and die, it remains a single seed.
But if it dies, it produces many seeds.
Do you guys know where it says that?
It says it immediately after this story, and immediately before Jesus, he was built in the resurrection.
So he tells us about Lazarus' death and resurrection.
Then he tells us what that means to die and come back.
Glory growing out of death.
And then he tells us his story.
So when he says to the disciples, um, I'm glad that you were an outlaw that there so that you might believe.
What's he talking about believing here, right?
Christ is going to come back from the dead in a couple of weeks, right?
And when he does, he needs people to be able to see it.
Right?
He needs people to be able to conceive the things he needed them to believe.
So going up in line as we look through the story.
He comes, um, Jesus came, um, Elijah's been in the, in the grave for, um, four days.
And Jesus and his disciples stop at the end of time of death.
Now Mary and Martha, when they arrive, are going to have been sitting in shiver for four days.
Uh, this is a culture that is, of course, where death was all around you.
We did have a confessional class of person that pushed the blood away and sterilized it and prevented it from a short distance, you know, in a contained way.
And so any person would have to develop an explicit outer core to that.
You'd have to become numb to death.
And so what they did by was a class of person who came and helped you break through that numbness and guilt when you have a real personal love.
Professional mourners would come sit with you in the morning and help you overcome all your inhibitions against dealing with death, right?
So there's a seven-day mourning period where you're sitting in the house just dealing with that one fact that professional mourners and friends all come and sit with you and get you through your grief.
And it would be highly improper to go to the end of time to meet a celebrity, right?
Uh, it would not be, also it wouldn't be great for Jesus to come into town where all these people are and then they'll sort of dust them, you know, they might want to swing him.
So Marcia goes to the older family to meet Christ's day while the mourning goes on in her house and slips away.
And when Marcia comes out to see Jesus, she says in verse 21,
Lord, if you had been here, my brother wouldn't have died.
Um, she probably had gotten word back from the messenger that would have been sent for the messenger,
would have brought the sense of Jesus' message back to her saying,
Jesus won't end in death.
And she's grieving when she gets that message.
That's a tough lot to do, right?
Um, and so she said,
but if you've been there beforehand for what you're dying,
in those four days you're supposed to hear your brother will rise again, right?
And Marcia's a good disciple.
She remembers what John told us in chapter 5 that Jesus has taught that if the religious leaders of the day,
the educated and the wrong, in nice family, there is no resurrection.
Christ said, he gave this whole discussion in chapter 5 about how there will be a resurrection at the end of time
and everyone will be judged by God.
And he talks about how the, the, the dead will hear his voice and come forth.
And then actually there's a full commentary on rising from the dead that applies to Lazarus.
And Jesus told his disciples ahead of time so they could recognize Lazarus, uh, resurrection for it was.
So in time they could recognize his resurrection for it was, right?
And John has given us that same thing.
You see, when we're done here, you should go back home and read John 5, okay?
Um, so, but Marcia does know that and she knows there will be a resurrection to come.
So she responds in verse 24, I know that he will rise again on the last day in the resurrection.
Right?
I'm a good disciple.
I know that.
I paid attention and I believe you.
And Jesus says to her, he looks at grieving woman in the eye.
And this is the center of the center of the Lord, this verse.
This center story centers on this statement.
Jesus looked her in the eye and said, I may end the resurrection of the Lord.
Do you believe in me and you will live even if you don't live?
And everyone who lives and believes in me will never doubt it.
Do you believe this?
Did you just say she believed all the things you taught her in the past?
Now he looks at grieving woman in the midst of her loss and he's not with him and said,
death is at the end.
Do you believe that?
Right?
He said, it's not a future theological judgment concept.
It's me, present, now.
I'm the person and it brings life.
He said, you tell Jesus standing before him and saying, there will be more to life than
you know.
Do you believe this?
Right?
That's the life and life that it's like, right?
Have you believed?
She has never heard of Christianity, right?
She's never heard of Jesus over at the beginning.
She's hearing about sort of a precursor to it, right?
Yeah, so she has no basis.
And she says to him, Lord, I have to believe this.
The Christ, the Son of God, either of you who comes into the Word of me.
It's almost like I believe what my own belief, that statement that someone did.
She's believing as much as she can, right?
I believe in you.
I'm not exactly sure what you're saying.
And Christ doesn't prefer you, right?
He's kind.
He just, he's going to show her in a second, right?
When she said this, she went away and got her married, her sister married, secretly saying,
and I'm going to, right there it says in verse 1, 28, she wasn't called me,
secretly saying the teacher's calling for you.
People have asked why she did it secretly, like what does that mean?
The word secret there in the last word is, it's been used a couple of times in the assessment
when Herod was trying to hide the wise men from the people so there wouldn't be a worry
about the Messiah.
When Joseph was trying to put Mary away quietly so that he wouldn't be prosecuted,
there wouldn't become a public laughingstock.
When Paul was improperly punished by the civil authorities and they tried to sneak him out of
Congress so there wouldn't be a backlash.
Every time that word is used, it's about trying to control the backlash of public opinion, right?
So that's what we had, Mary, Martha here was trying to keep Mary from having negative public opinion
and backlash out of the body, which we used her morning food to go out and eat the four
breathing things at the time, right?
Now it's doubly important because just like the four days in the tomb, that meant Lazarus was
really going to be done.
This is not a set up John's time of this.
For those who are uncertain, he was really good.
He'd been in the grave for four days.
And nobody was trying to get people to go see Jesus at Lazarus tomb to see what happened.
So we're actively trying to prevent people from seeing Jesus at Lazarus tomb, right?
But Mary is an emotional person and rather than sneaking out the way Martha asked her to,
she jumps up and runs out of the building.
And I would like to go, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry.
So Mary runs to the tomb.
Of course, everyone seems that she's, if you run to the tomb, everyone seems she's running
to the tomb in other mornings as a supporter, so run out with her, right?
So all these people focused on Lazarus and Mary run out and instead of falling in tears
in front of the tomb, she falls in tears in front of Jesus at the other time.
This is unusual.
This is what Martha is saying to her.
And what do you hear I say to him in verse 32?
Lord, if you believe in my body, I wouldn't have done it.
He and Martha probably have had this discussion, in their grief.
And she's lying on the ground.
People are leaping at answers.
She's leaping into sleep.
And it says, Jesus was deeply moved.
He said, where did you lay him?
And they said, Lord, come see.
And verse 35, Jesus went.
You guys have probably heard this as the shortest verse in the Bible.
You may have heard that.
Jesus left.
It's not an accident.
There's a reason that translators set these two words apart of their own little verse
and likes to put content.
It's because the word weak here is not the same as what it wants.
It's the feeling or anything.
And I'm going to tell you a little personal language.
I don't want to pull away from it just to give you a sense of what that means.
When I was 15, 14, 15, I think, my parents were splitting up.
And I was a self-involved teenager.
So I was worried about probably popularity, definitely my jump shot, who I was dating.
I was ignoring my parents' party, right?
And it was a mid-year get-together with some friends of mine, kind of Christmas party people
I hadn't seen in a long time, good friends.
And in the midst of this celebration, Beverly, a very empathetic person, probably right now,
you know, that I hadn't seen in a while, sort of came up to me and left eyes with me
and, you know, kind of pulled us out of the environment around us and said,
how are you doing with all of this?
And I gave it to my mouth to say, what's funny?
What are you talking about?
And before I could say that, I was just boiling with tears, just flowing out of it.
And my emotion at that point was just complexity.
I was like, why am I crying?
You know, I had no idea.
It was very confusing.
But I was crying, my body reacting like a horse from your ass autonomically
because I hadn't dealt with this deep, well, the grief of loss of family, right?
And it was just overwhelming to me.
It took me by surprise.
I couldn't have stopped it.
And in verse 33, they said, 36,
the news said, oh, see how it is.
He loved them.
Because they saw this was out of his control.
He was just overwhelmed by the emotion at the moment, right?
In a way that he couldn't have predicted.
So in the same way, the eternal Messiah was standing before Mary saying,
there is life going to death.
Do you believe this?
And pulling her out of that.
In the next interruption of Mary, the total human is standing right there,
overwhelmed by the grief of loss of his friend.
And that's what John is telling him.
Holy God, holy man, he's telling you these things so you might believe
that there is life that he's done, as he told Martha.
So in the, it feels like he was deeply moved and went to the tomb.
I'm indebted to a while story professor who pointed this out,
and he was really good.
The way he's deeply moved there, it sounds to us like,
if we just read it quickly, Jesus was very upset
because he was very upset and so he went.
And then he went to the tomb.
There's more to it than that.
When he says deeply moved, the phrase he uses is what?
The way I would be deeply upset at maybe the next generation
who don't do it anyway.
I'm upset things are going.
So it's a sense of spencer, right?
And this is, it's phrased in the reflexes.
So you're sensuous as in itself when you're deeply moved, right?
That's interesting.
You guys may have had a, put an offering on a house,
a matter of fact, a business deal,
maybe a way you disciplined your style,
maybe a sports strategy, even when you're serious about a game,
where you've done something that you know is the right move.
But until it comes to fruition, the emotions carry you up, right?
The human side of you just can't deal with the uncertainty
before it actually happens.
It appears that that's what Jesus is going through here.
He's put the things to a lot, right?
He knows it's good.
He knows they're going to, he knows why is this going to be bad?
He knows he's going to be revealed in glory by these events, right?
He knows this is good for everybody.
You know, understanding, like you said to the disciples in verse,
back at the top in verse 9,
previously, we were told him,
we must carry out, in chapter 9, 4, 5,
we must carry out the works of whom he would fit me as long as it's going.
Night's coming when no one's going to work.
On the world, I'm in the light of the world.
That's what he told the disciples when they said,
when they're responding to the message that lies with an ear, right?
He said, after 12 hours in the day,
if anyone walks in the day,
he doesn't stumble because he sees the light.
If anyone walks in the night, he stumbles.
They were worried about death.
They were worried about being stoned.
He said, that's not the danger.
The danger is missing the opportunity to display the glory, right?
The danger is not revealing the eternal light to the world.
You're focused on something much simpler.
So, down below,
when he's deeply moved,
in 36, 38, thank you.
When he's deeply moved,
he's deeply moved because he's told them,
the stoning, the death,
it's not as important as the light, right?
The light that is the light of me.
And then, the light is the light of me.
And they're not quite sweet yet.
But it's important what they do.
And it was why, when he said,
I'm glad this happened,
so that you could see the glory of God,
they probably thought he knew it.
So, he said to Martha in verse,
or he's about to say it to her, right?
He said, he told Martha to bring the stone,
and Martha said, ooh,
you know, there's rot in there,
and deep humanization,
and we're sure we want to do this.
And Jesus said,
didn't I tell you,
but if you believe,
you will see the glory of God.
He's talking about himself revealed in glory,
the glory that persuaded John and Paul, right?
And John said,
I write these things to which you are believed.
It tells us to bring,
they don't believe it, right?
John wrote this as a teenager.
I mean, he experienced this as a teenager.
He wrote it as a seven-something-year-old man.
And he's been telling it to people for years,
60 years he's been telling people.
And they believe.
He's telling it because they believe.
At this moment,
Martha doesn't believe yet.
No one does.
But Christ is telling them,
you'll see my glory.
They think he means,
I'll do something glorious and miraculous.
And you will.
That's part of it.
What's actually going to happen
is that this resurrection of Lazarus
is going to kick into that's motion.
It's the catalyst
that brings his personal worth
against his death and resurrection
into court.
That's why it's the family of John.
It's the thing that he has this ministry.
These events kick through
the end of his life into motion,
which leads to him being revealed in glory.
So when he says,
do you want to see the glory of God?
That's what he's talking about.
So,
Martha had been removed the stone.
He uses this point.
Remember,
he had originally left town
because he said
that I and the father were warned
and they'd tell the stone.
So at this moment,
and Martha said,
I know that God will do anything
you ask of him.
So at this moment,
they would see that he's to say,
dear God,
please bring Lazarus.
What he actually says is,
nothing like that.
In a minute,
he's just going to command Lazarus
to come out of the grave.
But before that,
he takes a moment
to double down
on what was perceived as
blasphemy.
Right?
To make sure
that when you know
Lazarus was raised
in the grave,
it was raised to the dead
by a guy who said,
I am the father with one.
That's part of the story
that's going to go around.
He says,
Father,
in verse 41,
I thank you that you've heard me.
I knew that you always heard me,
but because of these people
standing around,
I said it so that
they may believe
that you sent me.
That's the whole prayer.
I'm with God.
Now,
with the power
and greed in me,
Lazarus come forth.
And he did.
Right?
That's the story.
And,
in this statement
verse of the year,
therefore many of the Jews
believed in him.
Therefore,
the Jews who'd come
to see Mary
and saw what he'd done
and they believed in him.
But some of them
went to the Pharisees
and told us what Jesus had done.
So that's not a but
that some believed
and some called the Pharisees.
They believed
and that was a really
positive outcome.
Oh,
but there was a seemingly
negative outcome,
which was that they
went and told the
religious leaders
that were looking for him.
Right?
And said,
he just raised someone
in the bed
and oh,
by the way,
declared himself
to be one of God
when he did.
Right?
So this next
that we're going
to read a little bit.
Therefore,
the result of that
in verse 47
is that the two priests
and the Pharisees
convened a council
and were telling
what are we going to do?
So this man
is performing
summons,
or this man
is performing
many summons.
If we let him
go on like this,
all men
will believe in him.
The Romans will come
and take away
both our place
and our nation.
They are
a couple of things here.
They are very concerned
that the Roman,
the Jews
will declare him
and follow him
in an insurrection
against the Roman
and they will be crushed.
Which, by the way,
that's true,
it happened 40 years later.
The Romans crushed them.
They don't want
that to happen.
And it really
crosses their mind
that he's actually
the Messiah,
it would appear,
right,
in their deliberation.
And even if he was,
this is not a good idea.
It's very,
very bizarre
to keep the country safe.
But this is not
the first time
Jesus raised things
in the dead.
Luke tells us
it up in Galilee
twice before it's happened,
right?
At the same time.
And this is not
the first time
he's declared himself
the one with the Father.
So why,
suddenly,
is the same angel,
the rulers,
the nation,
the capital city,
why are they convening
to talk about
this one Galilee?
And why are they
so upset?
What happened?
To give you context
for that.
Who's here
from a small town
in West Virginia?
Anybody?
What's the town on?
Barry?
Okay.
So,
Barry?
What was it?
Okay, so,
Barry?
It's Barry.
Okay, it's Barry.
All right,
Barry, what's your name?
Thank you,
I got that.
That was good.
You could have
just found a lie.
I got it.
Okay, so,
if someone was
raised from the dead
in your small town,
what would the
national press
in D.C. say?
They were so bold
to believe anything,
right?
That's what they would say.
There would be
a crazy humorous story
at the end of the night
we see it off
in West Virginia.
Here's a crazy story,
right?
Right, I'm right.
Now,
what if the same thing
happened in Alexandria?
Right?
And the next day,
the security guard
at CNN
was there
and some of his friends
and the secretary
at the law
of the congressman
was there
and the janitor
at the Smithsonian
was there
and they're just
pouring everybody
into town
and they're
credible witnesses.
What happens then?
The press appears,
the press knows
and they're deeply
interested in Jesus.
Now,
if the rulers
want to control
the press cycle,
if the government
wants to control
the press cycle,
they have a problem,
right?
They have lost
control of the conversation.
Very different.
So,
Jesus brought this
and every time
that they started
to stone him
or accuse him
of blasphemy,
whenever he broke
the law
or did something
it said they would
persecute him
or throw him out
of the synagogue,
whenever he was blasphemous
and it makes this
very clear
in chapter 6,
8 and 9 I think,
when he was blasphemous,
they tried to keep
up from him
and kill him
because it was
strictly law.
And now,
he always would
go away
unless the few
are settled down
because he would
say it's not my time.
Now it's time.
He said in verse 4
at the beginning,
it's time to the
same man to be glorified,
some God to be glorified.
So,
he's brought this
to the front door
of Jerusalem,
a sign they can't
ignore and a state
that they can't
ignore to go away.
So,
there's gathering
to talk about
what are they
going to do
about this.
If you let him go,
the Romans will come
and process.
But one of them,
Caiaphas,
this is in verse 49,
who was high-kissed
that year,
said to them,
you know nothing,
nor do you take
into account
that it is expedient
for you that one man
may die for a people
that the whole nation
may not perish.
Again,
the words of Jesus
that are coming
in just a little bit
unless the criminals
don't fall into the ground
and die that remains single
that it produces
many sins
once it closes
the ground and die.
Right in mind
is what Caiaphas is saying.
It's important
for one man to die.
Now he did not know,
he did not say
this is on the initiative.
This is John's season.
But being high-kissed
that year,
he prophesied
that Jesus was going
to die for the nation
and not for the nation
only,
but in order that he,
God,
might also gather together
into one children of God
all who were scattered abroad
so from that day on
they clung together
with children.
Now it's easy for us
to read that
and hear what John
said over that third time
like he didn't know
what he was saying.
It's still remaining
there's so much more
than you knew about.
You should not read
it that way.
Because 40 years
after the events
recorded here,
Rome did come
and confess Jerusalem
and the Sanhedrin
was gone
and the temple
and all the people
that relied on it
for their connection
to God
were scattered
throughout the empire
and they were reading
this letter
from John.
Right?
There's Gentiles
who are called in,
there are Jews
that are called in
and they're looking
for what happened.
How do I get back to God?
And then John
was assuring them,
this is a fantastic statement,
that Jesus was written.
Jesus was planted
in the ground
and came back glorified
and in the same way
that Lazarus
who died
and put the grain
and came back
and saved God's glory.
The temple
was destroyed
and something greater
of the kingdom of God
was growing out
of that thing
that was destroyed.
The kind of wheat
that comes to the ground
is dying.
And God is the word
of compassion
that he's spreading.
This is a really key moment
for the people
that are reading this
who are ignoring
the loss of the temple
and of Jerusalem.
And
there's word placed
throughout this
about gathering.
The Sanhedrin
means gathering
and he said
he's going to gather
together this elite
to put in place
the work of God
and make sure
it was done properly.
And he's saying
that's not what happened.
There was a larger gathering
and through these events
there would be destruction
and there would be growth
and from that
God would be able
to gather all people
into his own.
The elite
likely mentioned
they should not have been
gathered all people
that need to be gathered
to God
and these are the events
that made it happen.
I'm telling you
these things
so that you might
believe in such a day
and believe in
you might have
life in his name
just like life in it.
So he leaves town
again at the end
of this stuff
people are down
and they're like
a serious death
going out for him.
And once again
he leaves town
but only for a little bit
like a week or so
maybe a couple of weeks
he goes out
and you know
the first verse
of the chapter 12
comes right back
it's time for Passover now
so it was between
December and
you know
well it's going to be
Easter now
because of Jesus
instead of things
right
and the first time
is Passover
and between
Hanukkah and Passover
things are going to
happen
six days before Passover
Jesus comes back
and does he come back
quietly go into the city
celebrate Passover
and lead back to Galilee?
he does not
he has a seat
at Lazarus' house
with Lazarus
right
just picking things off
getting things right back
where he started
where he left him
right
therefore six days
before Passover
Jesus came to death
where Lazarus was
when Jesus was raised
from the dead
and they had dinner together
so he made the dinner there
Martha was serving
Lazarus was one of those
reclining at the table
with him
in verse 9
of that chapter
we see
that
a large crowd
of the Jews
from Jerusalem
had learned
that he was there
and they came
not for Jesus
only
but for very few
Lazarus
right
because he had been
dead
they want to see him
eat
the person that raised
him from the dead
right
and because
on the calendar
many of the Jews
were going away
and believing in Jesus
why were people
believing in Jesus?
because of the
resurrection Lazarus
these are
and so many
he seems to be
really my Lord is
so
at this point
what the high priest
feared was happening
the crowds
were beginning
to acclaim them
and in the next verse
on 12
he goes into Jerusalem
for Passover
people are flying
the streets
declaring him
Messiah
Sam Hosanna
which means
Lord save us
you
from the Romans
he needed to say
to them too
what he says
his disciples
the Romans
are for the danger
the danger
is missing
the light
from among you
right
it says
in John 1
he said
when he was
on his own
receiving
by the
too many
as his
instinct
because
then he gave
powers
to the things
of God
because
it took
a certain
amount
of insight
to represent
salt and temper
and I firmly believe
that he raised
Lazarus
from the dead
so that all
these people
would be talking
about him
so that they
used the sort
of thing
he could do
right
so that
when he
raised
from the dead
a few weeks
later
they're like
oh
that's a
possibility
right
you have to
consume it
before you can
believe it
and John's
telling you
what happens
so that we
too can
believe
so the
question
on this
of why
did Jesus
do these
things
and why
did John
write about
them
that was
the only
question
right
it seems
tragic
in 12
let's
can I
read it
to you
Judas Iscariot
one of his
disciples
was intending
to kill him
right
you guys
know
he said
when he opened
this up
he said
I want to
do this
I'm glad
you're going
to see
this
because
the son
of God
will be
glorified by
meaning
he will
be revealed
as the son
of God
by the
resurrection
from the
grave
although
they didn't
know
what
he said
you know
when he
then said
now is
the son
of God
glorified
because
that's
a quote
too
in
them
anybody
it's
when
Judas
got up
from the
last
chapter
to go
betray
him
to
the
two
priests
and
they
were
looking
for him
because
of
these
events
where he
resurrected
Lazarus
in
the
dead
right
so
this
is
the
past
glorification
that
John
laid
century
of
that
as
he's
talking
about
that
he
said
to
disciples
the
danger
in
the
getting
stoned
we
very much
get caught
up
in the
idea
there was a
great quote
the
idea
that
God
is
on
the
gate
if
he
rescues
you
from
your
circumstance
it
is
functional
to
the
resurrection
right
that's
what he
said
to
the
disciples
when
he
says
there's
light
in
the
day
it
doesn't
matter
about
the
stone
it
matters
about
spreading
the
light
while
we
came
right
and
to
do
that
he
looks
Martha
in
the
eyes
and
says
I
am
the
resurrection
of
life
in
verse
everyone
who
lives
and
believes
in
the
ministry
do you
believe
that
do you
believe
in the
glory
that
came
from
them
do you
actually
believe
the
righteousness
of
God
and
that
Jesus
will
rise
and
that
is
the
evidence
that
you
have
to
know
it
before
you
can
share
it
you
have
to
experience
it
before
you
spread
it
to
other
you
that
glory
so
I
would
say
the
center
of the
of
the
center
of
John
is
Jesus
looking
up
in
the
eyes
and
saying
do you
believe
ponder
on
that
this
week
okay
let's
pray
Father
God
I
just
thank
you
for
all
that
you
brought
to
us
at
this
church
the
opportunities
you've
given
spread
your
glory
to
the
things
that
you
did
not
think
that
the
way
did
and
that
great
and
that
you
begin
to
walk
and
believe
in
what
everything
does
thank
you
for
to
touch
on
it
just
to
touch
on
it
feels
like
human
friendship
when
you
walk
us
through
the
valley
of
the
shadow
of
death
and
suffering
the
morning
of
suffering
because
in
you
it
is
life
you're
and
peace
end
of
the
peace
and
Here we can just in our service of worship, we try to almost always end with some opportunity to respond to the preaching of God's Word.
I love to remember this communion, a communion in a very rare sense of a personal altar call every week we work, to come again and remember what He has done, and watch what He did watch, and the response to the preaching of the Word is naturally going to get ready for the homeless that were going to be here.
We try to bring them down, and hope that that is to invite someone to invite you to respond to the teaching of the Word. Thank you for preaching the genres, thank you for preaching to the Word, teaching it well, it was a feast.
For those of you who have been a long time believers, I've read about the community as a feast, and I guess there's a good look for it.
You know, there's a bunch of things you can do.
They have boxes up there, it's a lot of things you can grab a box about there, and care for a child across the globe, and there are many ways that you can respond.
But if I think I'd like to give an opportunity for those who are speaking, or who are in physical, who maybe have recently said yes to Jesus, or maybe have not yet said yes to Jesus.
But if I'm going to do it with a style of, like a hundred years ago, the way the gathering would be preaching, someone would come and preach, someone would come up with the words and confound the word.
And just give a consolation of one or two things that would add as the message, the gift for the context, someone would sit and listen to what was being preached, I mean, what is specific for us today that more of us need to hear again.
And I'd like to put two things out of the text messages if I can.
I'd like to put two things out of the text messages if I can.
I'd like to put two things out of text messages if I can.
He told us that John put this message here, and Jesus told this time here between the first three years and the last few weeks of the ministry.
And here's the second one.
Here's the third one.
He says that you must be able to conceive before you believe.
And the raising of God was the opportunity to conceive that God can raise again before God.
And I suspect that some of us really, maybe this message was the opportunity to conceive.
I think it's like a baby.
I'm not going to believe it because I just hate it.
I'm not going to believe it because I hate it.
I hate it because I hate it.
I hate it because I hate it because I hate it.
You may be a person who wants more.
She said something from his message and I think it's really critical, really helpful.
And then Jesus said, "I'm not going to believe it.
I'm not going to believe it."
I'm not going to believe it.
Because if you experience, I'm not going to believe it.
If you're not going to believe it.
I'm not going to believe it.